<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An Ancient and present state of Poland giving a short, but exact, account of the scituation [sic] of that country, the manners and customs of the inhabitants, the several successions of their kings, their religion, &amp;c., drawn out of their best historians : to which is added an impartial account of the death of the late king and the present election as it now stands.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1697</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 53 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 14 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A69464</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A3066</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R16140</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11928151</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11928151</idno>
            <idno type="VID">51063</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A69464)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 51063)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 48:5 or 1643:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An Ancient and present state of Poland giving a short, but exact, account of the scituation [sic] of that country, the manners and customs of the inhabitants, the several successions of their kings, their religion, &amp;c., drawn out of their best historians : to which is added an impartial account of the death of the late king and the present election as it now stands.</title>
                  <author>Savage, John, 1673-1747.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 23 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for E. Whitlock ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1697.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Previously attributed to John Savage by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Item at reel 1643:11 identified as Wing S766 (number cancelled).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of originals in the Huntington Library and the Trinity College Library, Cambridge University.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Poland --  History --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:51063:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:51063:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE ANCIENT AND PRESENT STATE OF POLAND.</p>
            <p>GIVING A ſhort, but exact, Account of the Scituation of that Country. The Manners and Cuſtoms of the Inhabitants. The ſeveral Succeſſions of their Kings. Their Religion, <hi>&amp;c. Drawn out of their beſt Hiſtorians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hich <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> added, An <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> of the late K<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> as it now ſtands.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> for <hi>E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hitlock,</hi> near <hi>Stationers-Hall,</hi> 1697.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:51063:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:51063:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER,</head>
            <p>THE Affairs of <hi>Poland</hi> being, at this juncture, the common Subject of our Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes and Expectations, upon the happy De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termining whereof, 'tis thought, the future Peace, Quiet and Proſperity, of <hi>Europe</hi> will, in a great meaſure, depend; The following Account may perhaps be acceptable to the Publick. It treats firſt in general of <hi>PO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LAND,</hi> how Bounded and Divided. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards of the Nature of the Country, and Manners of the People, the Election of their Kings, their Government, and their Religion. Theſe are the principal Heads upon which we make our Enquiries of any Country and Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. They are handled ſo briefly and ſuccinctly,
<pb facs="tcp:51063:3"/>as not to be tedious to the Reader, yet, 'tis hoped, to his Satisfaction. There is added an Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the Death of the late King, and of the preſent Election, as it now ſtands.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:51063:3"/>
            <head>THE Ancient and Preſent State OF POLAND, &amp;c.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I. <hi>Of</hi> Poland.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Poland</hi> is an Elective Monarchy, comprehending the Antient <hi>Sarmatia Europaea,</hi> and the Eaſtern part of <hi>Germany,</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the <hi>Viſtula.</hi> It is called by the Natives <hi>Polska,</hi> and has taken its Name from the Word <hi>Pole,</hi> or <hi>Pola;</hi> which, in the <hi>Selavonian</hi> Language, ſignifie, an Hunting Country; all this State conſiſting of vaſt Plains, Fields and Woods, proper for Hunting. It is much greater, and more conſiderable than it was, ſince <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thuania,</hi> and ſeveral other Provinces, have been added: For before it only contain'd what we now call the <hi>Great,</hi> and the <hi>Leſſer Poland:</hi> But with theſe Additions, 'tis one of the greateſt King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms in <hi>Europe. Moſcovy</hi> and <hi>Tartary</hi> lie to the Eaſt; <hi>Hungary, Tranſilvania</hi> and <hi>Moldavia</hi> to the South; <hi>Germany</hi> to the Weſt; and the <hi>Baltick</hi> Sea, <hi>Livonia,</hi> and a part of <hi>White Ruſſia,</hi> or <hi>Moſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy,</hi> to the North. This State may be divided into <hi>the Kingdom of</hi> Poland, and <hi>the Great Dutchy of</hi> Lithuania. <hi>The Kingdom of</hi> Poland is ſubdivided into <hi>Great,</hi> and <hi>Leſſer Poland:</hi> The <hi>Leſſer Poland</hi> lies
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:51063:4"/>betwixt <hi>Hungary, Sileſia</hi> and <hi>Ruſſia:</hi> In it is <hi>Cracow,</hi> the Capital City of all the Kingdom, and <hi>Sandomirz. Great Poland</hi> is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt <hi>Germany, Pomerania, Siliſia</hi> and the <hi>Leſſer Poland;</hi> and has the Cities of <hi>Poſnan, Kaliſch, Gneſna, Lencici, Lublin</hi> and <hi>Sirad:</hi> It contains alſo the Provinces of <hi>Mazovia,</hi> where is <hi>Warſaw</hi> and <hi>Pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>sko; Cujavia,</hi> where is <hi>Ulad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>v; Royal Pruſſia,</hi> which has <hi>Dantzick, Elbing, Thorn, &amp;c.</hi> and <hi>Black Ruſſia,</hi> with the Cities of <hi>Leopold,</hi> and <hi>Prezmiſle,</hi> in Latin <hi>Premiſtia. Lithuania</hi> has in it the Cities of <hi>Vilua, Novigrade, Poloczk, Minx, Wiſepezk, Miciſlaw, Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlaw, &amp;c.</hi> and is divided into <hi>Volbinia,</hi> with the Cities of <hi>Lucho, Klow, &amp;c. Podolia,</hi> with the Cities of <hi>Caminiec, Braclaw, &amp;c. Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſia,</hi> where is <hi>Breſſici;</hi> and <hi>Samogitia,</hi> the Capital of which is <hi>Med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niki. Poland</hi> is otherwiſe divided into Thirty four <hi>Palatinates,</hi> or Governments: Every <hi>Palatine</hi> has his <hi>Chaſtellans</hi> under him, and they are Captains and Governors of Cities, and are about Eighty ſeven in all. There may be an Eccleſiaſtical Diviſion of <hi>Poland,</hi> according to their two Archbiſhopricks of <hi>Gneſna</hi> and <hi>Leopold.</hi> They had formerly <hi>Riga</hi> too, but that City is now in poſſeſſion of the <hi>Suedes.</hi> The Archbiſhop of <hi>Gneſna</hi> is the Firſt Senator; he aſcends the Throne upon the King's Death, and governs till an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other is choſe. There are Fifteen Biſhooricks in <hi>Poland,</hi> many Abbies, and the Univerſities ot <hi>Cracow, Royaumont, Coningsherg, Zamoiski, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II. <hi>Of the Country of</hi> Poland.</head>
               <p>THE Air of <hi>Poland</hi> is very pure; and the Land ſo good, that it is almoſt impoſſible to conceive the Quantity of Corn they ſend to other Countries. There are vaſt Plains, as far as you can ſee, intermix'd with Rivers, and many Woods; which are to the Advantage, as well as Beauty, of the Country. This chiefly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns <hi>Great Poland:</hi> The <hi>Leſſer</hi> is as fruitful, though not ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pact: In it are Mines of Silver and Iron, and Vines, and excellent Fruits. With theſe Advantages, they likewiſe enjoy, a temperate
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:51063:4"/>Air. But it is not ſo in <hi>Lithuania:</hi> The Commodities in which they trade, are, Honey, Wax, Veniſon, Fiſh, Timber, Hemp, Corn, the Skins of Martins, Caſtors, Bears, Elkes, and other Wild Beaſts; as alſo Copper, Lead, Iron, and chiefly Steel.</p>
               <p>The Nobility only are conſiderable in <hi>Poland:</hi> The Third Eſtate are, in a manner, Slaves. The Gentlemen of <hi>Poland</hi> are large, and ſtrong; dexterouſly wield the Scimitar; Learned in Foreign Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages; very liberal, brave Men; and hearty <hi>Roman Catholicks.</hi> But it muſt farther be own'd, that they are fierce, and proud; that they ſacrifice every thing to their own Opinions; and own no Sovereign, but Liberty. From hence have come thoſe Advantages the <hi>Tartars</hi> and <hi>Moſcovites</hi> have had formerly againſt them; and the Reaſons why the King of <hi>Sueden,</hi> with about Forty Thouſand Men, reduced their Country to the laſt Extremity, when their Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies conſiſted of Two Hundred Thouſand Fighting Men: Which could proceed from no other Cauſe, than a Miſ-underſtang among themſelves, and the little Power they give their Prince: Inſomuch, that before the Senate can be aſſembled, and the Nobility have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to go to War, the Enemy has Time to do what he will in the Field; and there are no ſtrong Places to hinder his going to the Gates of <hi>Warſaw.</hi> However, the <hi>Polanders</hi> are good Soldiers, eſpecially the Horſe, who are armed with a Carabine, a Caſe of Piſtols, an Axe on one ſide, and Scymitar on the other, a Quiver full of Arrows and a Bow at their Backs, which they uſe after the the Diſcharge of their Firo-A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ns, when the Enemy flyes. The <hi>Polanders</hi> love Travelling; they are faithful, obliging, and civil to Strangers: They are rich in their Habits, and ſplendid in their Entertainments, which they make freely for their Friends.</p>
               <p>Their Marriages, eſpecially in the Countries of <hi>Pruſſia, Samogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ttia</hi> and <hi>Lithuania,</hi> are as follows; The Young Women do not marry before the Age of Twenty lour Years; or, at leaſt, not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they have wrought with their own Hands Cloth and Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to preſent every one that attends their Bridegroom to Church. When the Father ſeeks a Wiſe for his Son, he conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders neither Beauty, nor Fortune; but only her Manners, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhe be of an agreeable Age, if ſhe has a Body likely to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive and bear Children. Having found ſuch an one, ſhe is taken away by ſome of the Bridegroom's Kindred; after which, they apply for the Father's Conſent, to compleat the Marriage. Theſe People retain ſtill many Relicks of <hi>Pagan</hi> Superſtitions; for, in the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:51063:5"/>Functions or Ceremonies of Matrimony, they make the Bride go three times round the Fire, then ſit down, waſh her Feet, and with that Water ſprinkle the Bed and all the Moveables that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to the New-married Couple. They anoint the Bride's Mouth with Honey, cover her Eyes with a Veil, and ſo lead her Blindfold to all the Doors of the Houſe, which ſhe muſt ſtrike with her Right Foot. They throw Wheat, Rye, Oats, Barley, Rice and Beans at the Doors, ſaying, <q>That the Bride ſhall never want any of thoſe Grains if ſhe continues devout in her Religion, and takes Care of the Affairs of the Family.</q> That done, they take the Veil from before her Eyes, and have a Banquet; But at Night, when it is time to go to Bed, they dance, and cut off her Hair; then ſome of the Women wrap her Head in a white Linen Cloth, which ſhe may wear till ſhe have a Son born, for till then ſhe is called a Girl. Laſtly, She is taken to her Chamber; where, after being jocularly pinched and beaten, they deliver her to her Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groom, who they give to eat Goat or Bears Stones together, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of Sweet-meats and other Delicacies; which, they are of Opinion, help Procreation; and therefore, in their Marriage-Feaſts, they have no Fleſh of any Creature that was gelt.</p>
               <p>They uſe in their Diet, a good quantity of Saffron and Spices; and ſpare not for Sugar in many Diſhes peculiar to them.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Polanders</hi> are very devout, and faſt <hi>Wedneſdays, Fridays</hi> and <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turdays;</hi> but they ſcruple not being drunk, and to fight at theſe times. The Country-People are poor and miſerable, and are Maſters of nothing they have, but are ſubject to their Lords, who treat them as Tyrannically as Gally-Slaves. A Gentleman there has Power of Life and Death over thoſe of his Family, and Tenants: And if a Neighbour kills one, and pays the Value ſet upon him, all is well again: And when they ſpeak of a Gentleman's Riches, they reckon them by his Number of Tenants. The Houſes of theſe miſerable Slaves, who work hard, and live upon little, are only of Mud and ſome Trees to hold up the Roof. The Children ſleep and eat with the Swine; and the Maſter of the Houſe has no other place to eat in, and oftentimes for his Lodging, than the Manger and Rack where his Cattel are kept. 'Tis true, there is ſometimes a little Apartment next the Roof, where thep have a Stove, and the beſt of the Family lie upon Skins. They drink Beer, or Mead, but no Water, becauſe 'tis almoſt all ſtinking in <hi>Poland,</hi> where it corrupts in the Plains. Their Women are little, not handſom, very ſimple,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:51063:5"/>but civil: The <hi>Polanders</hi> love them, but treat them like Servants; and when they return home from the Army, they give them their Right Hands to kiſs. They are ſomething jealous, and therefore have no Converſation, but with their next Relations, unleſs when they are at Balls and Feaſts. They go very ſeldom abroad.</p>
               <p>There are no Inns in <hi>Poland,</hi> upon the Road; and therefore, Gentlemen that travel, either lodge with their Friends, or carry their own Proviſions along with them, or elſe lie upon the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try-People, who are obliged to receive them, and that as a Tax up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them. If any of the Nobility are taken in War, the King is obliged to ranſom him. Their Language is <hi>Sclavonian;</hi> beſides that, they all ſpeak Latin, and moſt of them underſtand Foreign Languages.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III. <hi>Of the Kings of</hi> Poland.</head>
               <p>IT is commonly thought the <hi>Huns</hi> were the firſt People that came into <hi>Poland;</hi> and the <hi>Sclavonians,</hi> who drove thence the <hi>Suedes</hi> and <hi>Goths,</hi> and ſome others that inhabited from the <hi>Viſtula,</hi> to the <hi>Elbe. Lechus</hi> made himſelf Maſter of it about the Year 550, and began the Monarchy of <hi>Poland.</hi> This Prince reſided at <hi>Gneſna,</hi> a City which he built, and ſo named from an Eagle's Neſt that was found on the top of a Tree where it was building; the Word, in the <hi>Poliſh</hi> Language, ſignifying <hi>a Nest:</hi> Whence came the Arms of the Kingdom to be a Spread-Eagle.</p>
               <p>The firſt Governors of this Country did not aſſume to themſelves the Title of Kings, but only that of Dukes; and the firſt Form of Government was very inconſtant; for, after the Race of <hi>Lechus,</hi> (though it be uncertain how many there were, and how long they govern'd, and what were their Atchievments,) Twelve Governors (in their Language called <hi>Vayvods</hi>) adminiſter'd the Government; who having refin'd this barbarous People by good Laws and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions, at laſt were divided among themſelves. Whereupon, the <hi>Poles</hi> elected one <hi>Cracus;</hi> who having reſtor'd the Common-wealth
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:51063:6"/>to its former State, built the City of <hi>Cracovia,</hi> (now <hi>Cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cow,</hi>) calling it after his own Name, and making it his Place of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidence. His youngeſt Son, <hi>Lechus</hi> the Second, to obtain the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipality, Murther'd his eldeſt Brother; but the Fact being diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd, he was baniſh'd. To him, ſucceeded <hi>Venda,</hi> a Virgin, only Child of <hi>Cracus.</hi> After her Death, the Government return'd to <hi>Vayvods;</hi> which continued till the <hi>Poles</hi> elected <hi>Premisbus,</hi> a Gold-Smith, called alſo <hi>Leſcus</hi> the Firſt; who obtain'd the Crown by a Stratagem that ſav'd the <hi>Poles</hi> when they were in diſtreſs; the Manner of which was thus; <q>They being in the Field, againſt the <hi>Moravians,</hi> and finding themſelves much inferiour in Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, this Goldſmith bethought himſelf of a Way to make the <hi>Poliſh</hi> Army ſeem more numerous; which was, by making a great Number of Shields of Barks of Trees, and afterwards ſmeering them over with Galls and Quick-Silver; which ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king a great Shew, and the <hi>Moravians</hi> really believing the <hi>Poles</hi> were equal in Number, ſtood gazing upon the Shields, till the <hi>Poliſh</hi> Army had Time to retire.</q>
               </p>
               <p>This Duke having no Iſſue, an Horſe-Race was inſtituted, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine the Succeſſion; and three Candidates appearing, one of them thinking by Subtilty to obtain the Crown, laid ſeveral Iron Spikes in the Way where the Race was to be run; which the the other two knowing nothing of, they gall'd, and ſtop'd in their Career, ſo that the Politician came firſt to the Goal: But the Fala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy being ſoon detected, a poor Country Fellow, that ran along with them, on Foot, only for his Diverſion, was choſen, and the other kiil'd upon the Spot.</p>
               <p>This Duke's Name was <hi>Leſcus</hi> the Second; and who (as ſome ſay) was afterwards ſlain in the Wars againſt <hi>Charles the Great.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To him ſucceeded his Son, <hi>Leſcus</hi> the Third; who having ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peas'd <hi>Charles the Great</hi> with Preſents, made Peace with him, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as an unequal Ally, or by acknowledging himſelf his Vaſſal. This Duke left <hi>Poland</hi> to his Son <hi>Pop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ell;</hi> but gave the neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring Countries of <hi>Pomerania</hi> and <hi>Caſſovia</hi> to his Natural Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren.</p>
               <p>After him, ſucceeded his Son, <hi>Pop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ell</hi> the Second; a very ill Man; who, by the Perſusions of his Lady, murther'd his Father's Brothers: Whereupon, 'tis reported, that our of their dead Bodies (which he would not ſuffer to be interr'd) came forth a great Number of huge Rats, which devour'd him, and his whole Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:51063:6"/>notwithſtanding all imaginable means were uſed to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent it.</p>
               <p>After his Death, came an <hi>Inter-regnum,</hi> full of Troubles, till the <hi>Poles</hi> declar'd <hi>Piaſtus,</hi> a Country-Fellow, born at <hi>Cruſwitz,</hi> for their Prince; from whom, ever after, if any of the Natives ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained the Royal Dignity, they were call'd <hi>Piaſti.</hi> His Poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity reign'd for a long time in <hi>Poland;</hi> from whom alſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended the Dukes of <hi>Lignitz,</hi> and <hi>Brieg,</hi> in <hi>Sileſia.</hi> 'Tis ſaid, this Duke was One Hundred and Twenty Years old when he died.</p>
               <p>His Son <hi>Zigmovitus</hi> was a brave and Warlike Prince; to whom ſucceeded his Son</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Leſcus</hi> the Fourth; of a peaceable Temper.</p>
               <p>Of much the ſame was his Son <hi>Zickmoviſtus,</hi> who ſucceeded him. This Prince had but one Son, who being born blind, was, in the Seventh Year of his Age, (in which Year, according to the Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom of thoſe Times, his Head was to be ſhav'd, and he to receive his Name,) reſtor'd to his Sight; which was then taken for an Omen, that he ſhould be enlighten'd with the Chriſtian Faith. His Name was <hi>Miciſlaus,</hi> or <hi>Miſcho;</hi> who began his Reign in 964. and was the firſt Chriſtian Duke of <hi>Poland.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Boleſlaus Chrobry,</hi> his Son, ſucceeded him in 999, and was crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted King by the Emperor <hi>Otho</hi> the Third, who viſited the Tomb of Sr. <hi>Adelbert,</hi> kill'd in <hi>Pruſſia.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He left the Crown to <hi>Miciſlaus</hi> the Second:</p>
               <p>Who likewiſe left it to <hi>Caſimir;</hi> who being an Infant, his Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Rixa</hi> took upon her the Adminiſtration of the Government; but the <hi>Poles</hi> being diſ-ſatisfied with her, ſhe was fore'd to flee, with her Son, into <hi>Germany,</hi> who, in his Journey afterwards to <hi>France,</hi> aſſum'd the Order and Habit of a Monk. During his Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence there were great Diſturbances in <hi>Poland;</hi> whereupon, by the Mediation of the Pope, the <hi>Poles</hi> prevail'd upon <hi>Caſimir</hi> to leave his Monaſtery, and to accept of the Crown; but upon this Condition, That they were yearly to contribute a Farthing for each Head, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept thoſe of the Nobility and Clergy, towards the maintaining a perpetual Burning Lamp in the Church of St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s at <hi>Rome;</hi> and moreover, cauſe their Heads to be ſhaved about their Ears, like Monks.</p>
               <p>His Son, <hi>Boleſlaus</hi> the Second, ſucceeded him. This Prince, ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam'd <hi>The Cruel,</hi> put to death <hi>Staniſlaus,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Cracow;</hi> and,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:51063:7"/>as a Puniſhment for his Crimes. <hi>Poland</hi> loſt the Title of King for a conſiderable Time.</p>
               <p>The next King was <hi>Uladiſlaus</hi> the Firſt, Brother to the fore-going. <hi>Boleſlaus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He was ſucceeded by his Son <hi>Boleſlaus</hi> the Third, a brave Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier, who obrain'd a ſignal Victory over the Emperor <hi>Henry</hi> the Fifth, in the <hi>Dogs Field,</hi> near <hi>Breſlau.</hi> There never was a Prince in <hi>Poland</hi> more famous than this; he fought 45 Battels with Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs, except the laſt with the <hi>Red Ruſſians,</hi> which was loſt through the Cowardice of the <hi>Vayvod</hi> of <hi>Cracovia;</hi> to whom the King, for Recompence, ſent a Hare's Skin and a Spinning-Wheel; which ſo troubl'd him, that he hang'd himſelf: And the King likewiſe was ſo concern'd at his Defeat, that he not long after died with Grief.</p>
               <p>His Son <hi>Uladiſlaus</hi> the Second ſucceeded him.</p>
               <p>After whom came <hi>Boleſlaus Criſpus,</hi> his Brother; who receiv'd a great Overthrow from the <hi>Pruſſians,</hi> his Army having been miſ-lead into Moors and Bogs, through the Treachery of a Guide.</p>
               <p>Next ſucceeded his Brother <hi>Miciſlaus Senier;</hi> but he was ſoon de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed for Male-Adminiſtration.</p>
               <p>Then came his Brother, <hi>Caſimir</hi> the Second, to be elected; who was only famous for chaſtiſing die <hi>Pruſſians.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>His Son <hi>Leſcus</hi> the Fifth, Sur-nam'd <hi>The White,</hi> was fain, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend with the baniſh'd <hi>Miciſlaus</hi> for the Kingdom.</p>
               <p>Next him, came his Son <hi>Boleſlaus</hi> the Fifth, Sur-nam'd <hi>The Chaſte;</hi> in whoſe Reign the <hi>Tartars</hi> committed prodigious Barbarities in <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and from thence made an Inroad into <hi>Sileſia,</hi> where, in a Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tel fought near <hi>Lignitz,</hi> they ſlew ſo many of the Inhabitants, that they fill'd nine great Sacks with their Ears, though they did cut off but one from each Head.</p>
               <p>To him ſucceeded his Couſin <hi>Leſcus,</hi> Sur-nam'd <hi>The Black,</hi> who was very fortunate in his Wars; though the Civil Commotions, and frequent Incurſions of the <hi>Tartars,</hi> occaſion'd great Diſturban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in his Kingdom.</p>
               <p>After his Death, there were great Conteſts, about the Regency; till at laſt, <hi>Premiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aus,</hi> Lord of <hi>Great Poland,</hi> got the Upper Hand, aſſuming the Title of King, which had not been uſed for near Two Hundred Years before. This Prince was murther'd by ſome <hi>Bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nburgh</hi> Emiſſaries after he had reign'd but Seven Months.</p>
               <p>Next to him, was elected <hi>Uladiſlaus Lecticus,</hi> who was depos'd for Male-Adminiſtration.</p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:51063:7"/>
               <p>Then came <hi>Wenceſlaus,</hi> King of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> to be choſen; but after his Death, <hi>Lacticus</hi> was reſtor'd.</p>
               <p>After him, his Son <hi>Caſimir the Great</hi> ſucceeded; who ſubdu'd all <hi>Ruſſia,</hi> and united it to the Kingdom of <hi>Poland.</hi> He dying, the Male Race of <hi>Piaſtus</hi> loſt the Crown of <hi>Poland,</hi> which, after this <hi>Caſimir,</hi> devolv'd to <hi>Lewis,</hi> King of <hi>Hungary,</hi> who left two Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hedwigis,</hi> the youngeſt of which, was declared Queen, and married <hi>Jagello,</hi> Duke of <hi>Lithuania,</hi> who was then Baptized, and made a Chriſtian. Upon this Marriage he was Acknowledged, and his Countries joined to <hi>Poland</hi> about the year 1386. <hi>Jagello,</hi> who took at his Baptiſm the Name of <hi>Uladiſlaus</hi> the 4th. had for his Succeſſor <hi>Uladiſlaus</hi> the 5th. This King was killed in a Battle againſt the <hi>Turks;</hi> in his ſtead <hi>Caſimir</hi> the 4th. was made King of <hi>Poland,</hi> to whom Succeeded his Son <hi>John Albert<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>;</hi> after whom came his Brother <hi>Alexander,</hi> who Reigned only five Years, when came <hi>Sigiſmund</hi> the Firſt, one of the moſt famous Princes in his time; his Son <hi>Sigiſmund</hi> the 2d. was next Elected, who died with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Iſſue, and thereby the Male Race of the <hi>Jagellonick</hi> Family was Extinct.</p>
               <p>Then the <hi>Polanders</hi> choſe <hi>Henry,</hi> Duke of <hi>Anjou,</hi> Son of <hi>Henry</hi> the 2d. of <hi>France,</hi> King, and he was Crowned the 15th. of <hi>Feb.</hi> 1574. But this Prince having Notice of the Death of his Brother, <hi>Charles</hi> the Ninth, King of <hi>France,</hi> he went to receive that Crown in 1576.</p>
               <p>Then one Party of the Electors ſet up <hi>Stephen Batori,</hi> Prince of <hi>Tranſilvania;</hi> and the other, <hi>Maximilian,</hi> Arch-Duke of <hi>Auſtria;</hi> which brought a War upon the Country. The Firſt carried it, and died without Childrin, in 1580.</p>
               <p>Next <hi>Sigiſmund</hi> the Third, Son to <hi>John,</hi> King of <hi>Sweden,</hi> was ſet upon the Throne in 1587, but the King, his Father, dying ſoon af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, he went to take poſſeſſion of the Crown of <hi>Sweden.</hi> Some time afterwards the <hi>Swedes</hi> revolted, and choſe <hi>Charles,</hi> Prince of <hi>Sudermania,</hi> his Uncle, for their King. They went to War with <hi>Sigiſmund,</hi> took <hi>Riga</hi> from him in 1625, and he died in 1632. <hi>Ula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſlaus,</hi> his Son, ſucceeded him, who dying in 1648, they choſe in his place <hi>John Caſimir;</hi> he made a voluntary Abdication of the Crown, and had for his Succeſſor <hi>Michael VVitznowizki,</hi> that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in 1672, and <hi>John Sobieski</hi> ſucceeded him, and died in 1696. This Prince was the Third of that Name; he was the youngeſt
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:51063:8"/>Son of <hi>Sobieski,</hi> Palatin of <hi>Cracovia, &amp;c.</hi> and of a Daughter of <hi>Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſlaus Zolkiewski,</hi> Grand Chancellor, and Grand General of the Crown. He was made Grand Marſhal of the Crown, <hi>Auguſt</hi> 24th. 1665, and Grand Maſter of the King's Houſhold, Palatin of <hi>Cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covia, &amp;c.</hi> He recovered 60 Towns from the rebellious <hi>Coſacks</hi> in the <hi>Ukrain</hi> in 1667, he held out <hi>Podhois</hi> againſt the <hi>Tartars,</hi> and two years after he took from them and the <hi>Coſſacks</hi> all the Palati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate of <hi>Bracklaw,</hi> in the <hi>Lower Podolia.</hi> He defeated the <hi>Turks</hi> in 1671, during the ſiege of <hi>Leopold,</hi> upon the <hi>Peltaw,</hi> in the <hi>Black Ruſſia,</hi> and in 1673 won the famous Battle of <hi>Cherzim,</hi> upon the <hi>Neiſter,</hi> upon the Frontiers of <hi>Moldavia:</hi> That Battle begun upon a <hi>Saturday,</hi> and was not fully over till within three days after, at what time it was ended by the Surrender of that that Fortreſs. The <hi>Turks</hi> in that Battle loſt 8000 <hi>Janiſaries,</hi> and 2000 <hi>Spahi's,</hi> which being one of die moſt celebrated Victories in this Age, was gained upon the 11th. of <hi>Nov.</hi> the next day after the deceaſe of King <hi>Michael Korilut Wiesnowiski.</hi> The Grand Marſhal <hi>Sobieski</hi> was Elected, <hi>May</hi> 10. 1674, but was not Crowned till fifteen Months after, during which time he gained ſeveral Advantages over the <hi>Turks,</hi> and conſtrained them to make a Peace at <hi>Zurowna.</hi> Every one knows how much he contributed towards the Raiſing the Siege of <hi>Viena,</hi> being himſelf in Perſon at the Action, wherein he acquired great Renown. He eſpouſed <hi>Mary de la Grange,</hi> the Daughter of the Marquiſs <hi>d' Arquien,</hi> not long ſince made a Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal, of the Noble Family of <hi>de la Grange</hi> in <hi>Nivernois;</hi> ſhe was the Widow of Prince <hi>Zamoiski.</hi> The King had ſeveral Children by her, and among the reſt three Princes, of which the Eldeſt has the Honour to be Brother-in-Law to the Emperor, by Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying one of the Princeſſes of <hi>Neuburgs:</hi> Laſtly, to compleat his Encomium, he ſpoke ſeveral Languages, and was a great Lover of Books, and Learned Men.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:51063:8"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IV.</hi> Of the Government, and Manner of Election in <hi>Poland.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>POland</hi> is a State where the Government is Monarchical, and Ariſtocratical. It is Monarchical, becauſe they have a King; and Ariſtocratical, by reaſon their King is not an Abſolute Prince, that can Diſpoſe and Reſolve upon Affairs by his own Power with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Conſent of the Senators. I have already taken Notice, that the Archbiſhop of <hi>Gneſna</hi> is Primate of the Kingdom, and has the Adminiſtration, during an <hi>Inter-regnum.</hi> He Aſſembles the States to Elect a new King, and Appoints both Time and Place. After every one has given his Suffrage, the King is Elected by Majority of Voices. This Prelate declares him, brings him forth into the middle of the Aſſembly, then he is Conducted to the Church, where, after Maſs, he Swears to preſerve the Privileges of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and to keep the Eſtabliſhed Laws, which oblige him to do nothing without Conſent of the States. Upon Matters Of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the King ſends, by his Chancellor, Letters to the Palatins, called <hi>Inſtructionis Litterae,</hi> becauſe they mention the State of thoſe Affairs his Majeſty has to propoſe to the Aſſembly, and Appoints them a Time to come to Court: When they receive theſe Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, every one of the Senators particularly examines the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, Quality, Subject and Conſequences of the Propoſitions, to which he has a Liberty to Anſwer as he ſhall think fittting, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with reſpect to the publick Good, or his own private Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt. The King ſends Letters alſo into the <hi>Palatinates,</hi> where the Nobility aſſemble to chooſe one among them, a Perſon of Merit, that is ſufficient and capable to ſpeak in behalf of their Province, in whom they are univerſally to agree to: For if it happens there be one Negative in the Aſſembly, 'tis impoſſible to proceed far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the Deputy cannot go, and that Province has no Voice in the States. After theſe Provincial Aſſemblies are over, the Sena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors and Deputies appear at Court at the Time prefixed, where the King, attended by his Chancellor, ſignifies to them firſt the Cauſe of their Meeting, then hears and receives their Advices, but
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:51063:9"/>they muſt be unanimous in their Reſolutions, or, as they ſay, <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine reclamante, nemine diſſentiente,</hi> or the Diet breaks up, every one goes home again, and the Propoſitions come to nothing. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Cities, there are only <hi>Cracow, Danzic</hi> and <hi>Vilna</hi> that have the Privilege of ſending Deputies to the Diet. The ordinary Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters are Tranſacted before the Judges eſtabliſhed in every <hi>Palati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate,</hi> and, as in the Provincial Aſſemblies, all manner of Perſons have Liberty to be preſent, and hear what is propoſed, the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Country-man may know all. So when ever they Treat of War, the Enemy is adviſed and informed of their Deſigns, their Strength, and how to ruine them. The King's beſt Revenue conſiſts in the Salt-works near <hi>Cracow,</hi> in the Mines of Copper, Lead and Silver, in the Fiſhery, and Tribute of the Jews, His Revenues are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted at 600000 Crowns <hi>per Ann.</hi> The Proſit ariſing from his Demeſnes are commonly given away in Penſions and Bounties, to the Palatines, Chaſtellains, and other Great Men, to engage them to his Intereſts. Moſt of what comes into his own Coffers, is ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther laid up, or Expended in the Purchaſe of Eſtates for his young<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Sons; his Daughters being Married at the Publick Charge; and the Expences of his Houſhold defrayed by his Subjects.</p>
               <p>He has the Nomination of the Biſhopricks, and of all the Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities of the Kingdom, and of the Commiſſions of War and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venue, the Courts of Juſtice, and Civil Government. The chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Dignities are the Lieutenant, the Great Maſter of the King's Houſhold, the Great Treaſurer, the Great Provoſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Theſe Places are both for the Kingdom of <hi>Poland,</hi> and Dutchy of <hi>Lithu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ania,</hi> where the King goes every two or three Years to hold a Diet; and as ſoon as he enters upon the Country, he is only ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by the Officers of the Dutchy. The Grand Marſhal of the Crown, or Crown General, has very great Advantages, and his Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice gives him the Title alſo of Grand Maſter of the King's Houſe, Great Maſter of the Ceremonies, Introductor of Ambaſſadors, Judge and Maſter of the Civil Government; he can make Laws, and has Power of Life and Death in him. The Generals of <hi>this Kingdom,</hi> and of <hi>Lithuania,</hi> may fight as they ſee Cauſe, and have Soveraign Power in the Camp. Beſides the Palatines and Chaſtel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lans that I have ſpoke of, there are in all the Cities, Burghers, Judges and Magiſtrates. But there lies an Appeal from them to <hi>Cracow</hi> for <hi>Great Poland,</hi> and to <hi>Lublin</hi> for the <hi>Leſſer Poland</hi> and <hi>Ruſſia.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:51063:9"/>
               <p>Tho' the King of <hi>Poland</hi> has the name of a King and the firſt Dukes were in truth Kings without the Title; yet at preſent he is nothing leſs, being not allowed to make Peace or War, to impoſe Taxes, make Laws, alienate any of his Demeſnes, or in ſhort, to do any thing of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance which concerns the Publick, without the conſent of the Diet. And he does not only ſwear to do all this, but allows their Diſobedience, in caſe he violates his Oath, which makes the Subjects the Princes Judges, and this Kingdom a meer Ariſtocracy, or knot of petty Kingdoms under one Head.</p>
               <p>The Firſt Dukes indeed were abſolute Princes, and ruled after a Deſpotical manner, having power not only of the Eſtates of their Subjects, but of Life and Death without formalities of Law; yet when they once became Elective they loſt much of that power, which decayed ſo by degrees, that at laſt it came to nothing, <hi>magni nominis umbra.</hi> A Diminution which began firſt in the times of <hi>Lewis</hi> of <hi>Hungary,</hi> and <hi>Jagello of Lithuania,</hi> who to gain the ſucceſſion to the Kingdom contrary to Law, the one for his Daughter, the other for his Son, parted with many of their Royalties and Prerogatives to buy the Voices of the Nobility. Since which time the Nobility in all their Elections have limited and reſtrained tie Kings Authority, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged their own. Yet the King once choſen and enthroned hath ſole Power in many things, as in aſſembling the Diets, chooſing Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar Councellors, diſpoſing abſolutely of his Vaſſals and the Revenues of the Crown, to what uſe he pleaſeth. He alſo is ſole Judge of the Nobility in criminal Cauſes, which is a ſtrong Bridle upon them. By which, and either joyning with the Clergy, or well forming his party among the Nobility, he may do many things not ſtrictly legal; the power and influence he hath in the publick Government being in proportion to his Abilities and Dexterity in managing them.</p>
               <p>The Forces of this Kingdom conſiſt moſt in Horſe, whereof they are able to raiſe 160000. Their Infantry are generally <hi>German</hi> or <hi>Huagarians,</hi> whom they hire for mony, and are like o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mercenary Soldiers. For the raiſing the Horſe, the Gentlemen of the Country are obliged by their Tenure, not only to ſerve in Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon for the Defence of the Realm, but to maintain a certain number of Horſe in continual readineſs, eſpecially in thoſe parts next the Tartars, where their numbers are great, and with whom they many times joyn to afflict and haraſs their own Country.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:51063:10"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> The Religion of the <hi>Polanders.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe ancient Inhabitants of the Country were <hi>Idolaters,</hi> and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhiped he ſame Gods as the <hi>Greeks,</hi> the <hi>Rowans</hi> and <hi>Germans. Tertullian</hi> aſſures us in his Treatiſe againſt the <hi>Jews,</hi> that the Goſpel was then preached in <hi>Sarmatia:</hi> But we know it was not received in that <hi>Sarmatia,</hi> which is now <hi>Poland</hi> till the 10th. Century. <hi>Mici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlaus,</hi> or <hi>Misk<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> I. married <hi>Debraw,</hi> the Daughter of <hi>Boleſlaus,</hi> Duke of <hi>Bohemia;</hi> and was Baptized the 7th. of March in the Year 965, and 966. ſince that time the <hi>Polanders</hi> have always continued Chriſtians. <hi>Lutheraniſm</hi> and <hi>Calviniſm</hi> have been received among them, but have not not prevailed there as in other Countries. They came acquainted with them from <hi>John Huſs,</hi> and others in the 15th. Century, who came from <hi>Bohemia</hi> into this Country. <hi>Gregory Paul Miniſter of Cracow,</hi> preached <hi>Arrianiſm</hi> there about the Year 1566. but was driven thence by <hi>Sigiſmond,</hi> with <hi>George Blandrata, Lelius Socinus, Valentinus Gentilis,</hi> and ſome others. <hi>Fauſtus Socinus,</hi> who has given the name to the <hi>Socinians,</hi> came thither afterwards and left his Diſciples who are to be found there to this day. There are likewiſe ſome <hi>Lutherans, Calviniſts</hi> and <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> to be found in other parts of <hi>Lithuania.</hi> They have among them alſo <hi>Schiſinaticks, Greeks,</hi> and many <hi>Jews</hi> that are in ſome credit for their Wealth. They en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy ſome particular Priviledges, but you ſee them always intent up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their Profit and Uſury. They live miſerable without Eſtates in Land, and only enrich themſelves by Trade. The <hi>Polanders</hi> are zealous in their Religion, hear Maſs daily, and practice great Aus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terities upon themſelves during Lent.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:51063:10"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>GHAP. VI.</hi> A Relation of the Death of <hi>John Sobieski,</hi> late King of <hi>Poland:</hi> With an Account of the Preſent Election, as it now ſtands.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>JOhn Sobieski</hi> the late King of <hi>Poland,</hi> departed this Life the 17th of <hi>June,</hi> 1696. about nine a Clock at Night, leaving behind him his Queen and 3 Princes, <hi>(viz.) James, Alexander</hi> and <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> with a Princeſs who is married to the preſent Elector of <hi>Bavaria.</hi> In his life time he heaped up <hi>vaſt</hi> Riches, and Endeavoured to make the Crown Heredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary, but in vain.</p>
               <p>The King being Dead, which was notifyed by Expreſs to the Cardinal <hi>Radziowski</hi> Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Gneſna,</hi> Primate of the Kingdom of <hi>Poland,</hi> and Regent during the <hi>Inter-regnum,</hi> he repaired immediately to the Capitol, and made his pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Entry into <hi>Warſaw</hi> on the 24th of <hi>June,</hi> 1696. with the uſual Ceremonies; the firſt thing he did was to call together the Senators, Principal Miniſters and Biſhops, who met, and had Conference in his Preſence the 28 and 29th of <hi>June,</hi> 1696. and came to the following Reſolutions, <hi>(viz.)</hi> Firſt, To notify the Death of the King to the <hi>Caſtelleins,</hi> and that the grand Convocation for Electing a new King be fixed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the 29th of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> 1696. Secondly, That notice be given to the Foreign Princes. Thirdly, That the Frontier Garriſons be reinforced, and the Troops maintained out of the publick Revenue. Fourthly, That the Treaſurer of the Crown do regulate the deceaſed Kings Court. Fifthly, The Cardinal Primate recommended to the Treaſurer of the Crown the ſafety of Trinity Fort, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And Sixthly, He ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely promiſed to preſerve the <hi>Jura Matronatus Regia.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:51063:11"/>
               <p>The Cardinal Primate having thus taken the Government upon him (which of right belongs to his Eminence during the <hi>Inter-regnum</hi>) he has managed Affairs there ever ſince, much in favour of <hi>France,</hi> and againſt the Intereſt of the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There were at firſt, ſeveral Illuſtrious Perſons propoſed as Candidates to fill the Throne, <hi>(viz.)</hi> Prince <hi>James,</hi> Prince <hi>Alexander,</hi> two of the late King Sons, the Elector of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> the Prince of <hi>Vaudemont,</hi> the Duke of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> the Grand Mareſchal of the Crown, Prince <hi>Sapieha,</hi> the Prince of <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourg,</hi> the Prince of <hi>Tranſilvania,</hi> with the Prince of <hi>Conti,</hi> the Prince <hi>Don Livio Odeſchalchi,</hi> and the Prince of <hi>Baden</hi> the Elector of <hi>Saxony,</hi> not then being talked of.</p>
               <p>There being ſo many Pretenders, the Kingdom fell into Faction, and he that had the moſt Money ſeemed to have the beſt Intereſt, in the meantime the Armies of <hi>Poland</hi> and <hi>Lithuania</hi> Confederated, and Committed abundance of Hoſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, doing a World of Miſchief, being ſupported under hand by the Abbot of <hi>Polignac</hi> Ambaſſador of <hi>France,</hi> with Money. This put the Kingdom into a Flame, and occaſion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the general Convocation to be put off from time to time; but at length the Crown generally prevailed with the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federate Armies to ſubmit, having procured a round Sum of Money of the Queen <hi>Dowager,</hi> to be diſtributed amongſt them.</p>
               <p>This being done, matters became Calm; and the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Diets were held, which terminated, but not without heats.</p>
               <p>The general Diet was appointed, and the overture made on the 15th of <hi>May,</hi> 1697. with the accuſtomed Ceremony, firſt the Popes Nuncio ſolemniſed the Maſs of the holy Ghoſt. After which the Biſhop of <hi>Poſcow</hi> made a Sermon exhorting the Aſſembly to mind the intereſt of the republick, and lay aſide all private Advantages, and to Advance to the Throne whom they ſhould deem moſt Worthy.</p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:51063:11"/>
               <p>The firſt thing the Aſſembly did, was to make choice of a Speaker, but that took up a conſiderable time, becauſe all the Deputies were not at firſt came up, but in Concluſion the Sieur <hi>Bilinski,</hi> a Perſon of Polite Learning and Ability was Elected, but the lower Nobility being Jealous that he was in the intereſt of <hi>France,</hi> threatned to cut him in Pieces if he ſhould move the advancing a <hi>French</hi> Man to the Crown: However we find ſince that he did not in the leaſt promote the Intereſt of the Prince of <hi>Conti,</hi> which plainly Demonſtrates that he favoured the promoting of ſuch as ſhould be propoſed by the Emperor and his Allies. Note that this Election began the firſt of <hi>June,</hi> New Stile, and laſted till the 16th of the ſame Month before the Suffrages could be collected and told, this Affair which was only looked upon as a preliminary, took up a whole Month.</p>
               <p>The next thing they were to do, was to give Audiences to the Foreign Miniſters, which they Commenced, on the 20th of <hi>June; Siegnior Davia</hi> the Popes Nuncio being firſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, and next to him the Biſhop of <hi>Paſſau,</hi> the Emperors Extraordinary Ambaſſador, and the reſt in their turns.</p>
               <p>The One and Twentieth of <hi>June</hi> being come, none could then Conjecture who ſhould be Elevated to the Crown, many of thoſe firſt propoſed, not being ſo much as mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
               <p>Prince <hi>Don Livio Odeſchalchi,</hi> who had propoſed the moſt advantageous terms to the Republick, was alſo not thought fit to Sway the Crown: They wanting a Warlike Prince, whoſe Name was Terrible to the Infidels, to be King.</p>
               <p>As for the Duke of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> there was two main Obſtacles that hindred them from making Choice of him: Firſt, his tender Age; and the ſecond, becauſe the Houſe of <hi>Lorrain</hi> having their Territories, could not Expend ſuch large Sums as was neceſſary for the purchaſing Suffrages.</p>
               <p>And upon the whole, it was thought that the Party of
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:51063:12"/>the Prince of <hi>Conti,</hi> and that of the Prince of <hi>Baden</hi> was the ſtrongeſt; yet ſome were of Opinion, that the Party of Prince <hi>James</hi> did over-ballance that of the Prince of <hi>Conti:</hi> ſo that the <hi>Poles</hi> were afraid then of a double Election, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs they could pitch upon a Third Perſon to the ſatisfaction of both ſides; which was hardly to be done.</p>
               <p>There was no Diſcourſe all this while of the Heroick Elector of <hi>Saxony;</hi> but he being arrived at <hi>Dreſden,</hi> which is his Capitol, the beginning of June, he muſtered his Troops, to the number of 10000 Men, and inſtead of going for <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gary</hi> to Command the Imperial Army, he marched with them to <hi>Breſlau</hi> in <hi>Sileſia,</hi> where he explained his deſign of ſtanding a Candidate for the Crown of <hi>Poland;</hi> which was an Amazement to moſt People, becauſe of his Religion, he being looked upon to have been a Proteſtant; but it ſoon ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared otherwiſe; for he had turned <hi>Roman Catholick</hi> at <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enna</hi> 18 Months before, which induced the Pope's Nuncio to ſpeak in his behalf at the Diet; ſo that then it was no Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret.</p>
               <p>The Day of Election being come, which was the Twenty Sixth of June, they drew out into the Field, and being come to the Place appointed, the Biſhop of <hi>Ploſcow,</hi> and thoſe of his Palatine, flung up their Caps, and cried out, <hi>Vivat Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deus;</hi> but they were immediately ſurrounded, and threatned to be Cut in pieces with Cimitars, it not being their turn to ſpeak.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Conti</hi>'s Party finding thus, that they were not ſtrong enough to Elect him, ſent to the French Ambaſſador to let him know, that if he would conſent to it, they would give their Suffrages to Elect any other, offering to return him the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menſe Sums which they had received of him, but he inſiſted to have the Prince of <hi>Conti</hi> Elected, according to his Inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons from his Maſter.</p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:51063:12"/>
               <p>Whilſt theſe things were in Agitation, the Primate and the Biſhop <hi>Ploſcow</hi> Elected the Prince of <hi>Conti,</hi> and cauſed him to be proclaimed, and immediately retired out of the Field, and went to the Cathedral at <hi>Warſaw,</hi> where they Sung <hi>Te Deum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Upon which the Favourers of the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that the Prince of <hi>Conti</hi> had but Fourteen Voices more than the Elector of <hi>Saxony,</hi> or Prince <hi>James,</hi> they reſolved to unite their Suffrages in favour of his Electoral Highneſs, by which means he had One and Twenty Voices more than <hi>Conti.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This raiſed up the drooping Spirits of thoſe that were in the Intereſt of the H. of <hi>Auſtria</hi> againſt that of <hi>Bourbon,</hi> to that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, that they cauſed inſtantly the Biſh. of <hi>Cujavia,</hi> at the Head of that Party, to repair in all haſte to the Cathedral at <hi>War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaw,</hi> where he entred with a Numerous Train; but finding the Doors ſhut by order of the Cardinal Primate, the Popes Nuncio cauſed them to be broke open; and Proclaim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Frederick</hi> Auguſt Elector of <hi>Saxony,</hi> King, with accuſtom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Ceremony, <hi>Te Deum</hi> was likewiſe Sung the ſame day.</p>
               <p>The Elector's Party went into the Field the 27th and the 28th, but that of the Prince of <hi>Conti</hi> never appeared after the firſt day, ſo that his Party viſibly fell off daily, particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly the Senators; ſo that Two Hundred Forty Three Stand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards declared for his Electoral Highneſs, and but Thirty Four for <hi>Conti.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Party of the Elector upon this drew up the Concor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>date which the King is to Sign, and agreed to ſend a formal Deputation to <hi>Breſlau,</hi> to invite the Elector to accept of the Crown.</p>
               <p>The four Mareſchals have declared in his Favour alſo.</p>
               <p>The Biſhop of <hi>Cujavia</hi> made a ſolemn Proteſtation againſt the unlawful Election of the Prince of <hi>Conti,</hi> without the gain-ſaying of any. The Royaliſts fired through the Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:51063:13"/>of the Cardinal Primate's Palace as they paſſed by, ut<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tering many Contumacious words againſt his Eminence.</p>
               <p>On the 4th of <hi>July</hi> the great Embaſſy, conſiſting of four Senators, accompanied by a great number of the Nobility and Gentry, went from <hi>Warſaw</hi> for <hi>Breſlau</hi> in <hi>Sileſia,</hi> to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratulate the New King, and to Conduct him to <hi>Crakau</hi> to be Crowned.</p>
               <p>On the 5th of <hi>July</hi> the Waywade of <hi>Vilna,</hi> the great Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſchal of <hi>Lithuania,</hi> the Crown Treaſurer, and the Biſhop of <hi>Ploſcow,</hi> as Partiſans of the Prince of <hi>Conti,</hi> conferred with the Generals who are for the Elector of Saxony, in order to adjuſt matters, but to no purpoſe, the Adherents of <hi>Conti</hi> refuſing to deſert him, threatning the Republick with a War from <hi>France,</hi> though he ſhould be neceſſitated to make Peace with the Allies.</p>
               <p>The Miniſter of <hi>Saxony</hi> having received a Million of Crowns, diſtributed ſome of it among the Army, which gained them intirely to the ſide of his Electoral Highneſs, and to promiſe to ſtand by him with their Lives and For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes; and in a word, they made Rejoycings upon his Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, and diſcharged all their Cannon Thrice, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Criticks make ſtrange Conjectures at the ſtriking of the Thunder-bolt in the Elector's Cloſet at <hi>Dreſden,</hi> and at the ſame time in his Houſe at <hi>Vienna;</hi> it being the very hour he was Elected King of <hi>Poland.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Elector's Party have left no Stone unturned to bring over <hi>Conti</hi>'s Party; and as an Expedient they ſent for the Elector's Miniſter to the place of Election by above an Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Deputies, where he produced an Atteſtation that the Elector his Maſter was turned <hi>Roman</hi> Catholick, thanked them for their Election, telling them, that his Maſter, pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuant to his promiſe, would pay the Ten Millions of <hi>Poliſh</hi> Florins, that he would maintain Six Thouſand Men at his own Charge, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Upon which the Party of his Electoral
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:51063:13"/>Highneſs, bound themſelves with an Aſſociation to ſtand by him, and not change their Minds.</p>
               <p>I preſume it will not be amiſs, to inſert here the ſubſtance of a Letter, which the Cardinal Primate ſent the day after the Election to the Elector, wherein among other things he inſerts what follows, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <hi>We thought not to diſpoſe of the Care of our Kingdom to your Electoral Highneſs, who is now taken up with Heroick Actions againſt the Common Enemy of Chriſtendom, for which reaſon we requeſt your Electoral Highneſs, not to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of this nomination as unanimous, but according to your innate Generoſity, and out of Love to the neighbourhood, to let us remain in Peace with our free Election of our King</hi> De Conti. <hi>If your Electoral Highneſs make any ground on the unity of the Generals, and the great Emulation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them and the Republick; you may be aſſured the more firmly, we have reſolded not to accept of the King by them propoſed,</hi> &amp;c.</q>
               <p>The Expreſs diſpatched with this Letter, returned with it unopened, becauſe the Addreſs was to the Elector, and not King.</p>
               <p>The Cardinal Primate has remonſtrated to all the Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring Princes; that the Election of the Elector of <hi>Saxony</hi> to be King of <hi>Poland</hi> is void, it being contrary to the known Laws of the Land, but they take no Notice of it. But on the other hand the <hi>Czar</hi> of <hi>Muſcovy</hi> and ethers threaten the republick with a perpetual War; in caſe they ſhould Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance a <hi>French</hi> Man to the Throne.</p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:51063:14"/>
               <p>The Elector of <hi>Saxony</hi> now King of <hi>Poland</hi> being gone from <hi>Breſlau</hi> to <hi>Tarnowitz;</hi> he had advice that the great <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſy</hi> of <hi>Poland,</hi> were approaching on the 21ſt, and on the 23d his Majeſty rendred himſelf without the Gate; where an Elevated place was Erected, covered with green Bows; and hung with Tapiſtry, and a Throne Erected under a Velvet Canopy richly Adorned. The King was very finely Dreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, his Cloaths being Decked with Diamonds; ſo that his Suit was ſaid to be worth a Million. The <hi>Embaſſy</hi> being ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived, they were Conducted to the King with the Sound of Trumpets and Kettle Drums. His Majeſty ſtood under the Canopy with the Biſhop of <hi>Paſſau</hi> on his Right Hand, and the Prince of <hi>Furſtemburg</hi> on his Left, one of the Prime Miniſters Conducted them to the Throne, where after a profound Reverence delivered their Credentials, which were read; after which the firſt Ambaſſador, being the Wayvode <hi>Wylinski</hi> for <hi>Poland,</hi> Commenced his Speech in Latin; and having Extolled the King's Perſon, and his great Qualities, he intimated the reaſons of their Arrival. The 2d Ambaſſador having the Wayvode of <hi>Witegiski</hi> for <hi>Lithuania,</hi> did the like; as did alſo the 3d Ambaſſador, who is the <hi>Staroſt</hi> of <hi>Zydaizoiw,</hi> in the Name of the Nobility. Then the King commanded the Baron <hi>Fleming</hi> to Anſwer them in Latin.</p>
               <p>On the 27th the new King with the Court, and the <hi>Embaſſy</hi> broke up from <hi>Tarnowitz</hi> for the Frontiers of <hi>Poland</hi> in order to go to <hi>Crakaw,</hi> where he is to be Crowned the 15th of <hi>September:</hi> He is to be called <hi>Auguſtus</hi> the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond.</p>
               <p>Since the new King is arrived at <hi>Crakaw,</hi> where he was received with the Loud Acclamations of the People; and he has Drawn together there upwards of 20000 Men, and is Diſpoſing all things for his Coronation, having ſworn to the <hi>Pacta Conventa.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:51063:14"/>
               <p>Yet notwithſtanding, the Cardinal Primate does not deſiſt from promoting the intereſt of the Prince of <hi>Conti,</hi> having ſummoned the Nobility to meet the 26th. of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending to proceed to a new Election, but it will ſignify nothing; the Elector of <hi>Saxony</hi> having already poſſeſſion, not only of the Kingdom, but alſo of the Crown; and on the other hand, the <hi>Czar</hi> of <hi>Muſcovy</hi> offers to aſſiſt him with 60000 Men to make good his pretentions, and the Elector of <hi>Brandenburgh</hi> with 16000. So that we may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, that this Election will terminate without the Effuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Blood in Favour of his Electoral Highneſs now King of <hi>Poland.</hi>
               </p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
